computer wonderful we're back right
thank you this has been such a rich
conversation already and we've got a few
more questions left well we could
actually go on for days I think we could
and I hope you come back to me okay
sometime yeah I was snorkeling trip in
kilometers then one of my favorite
memories when we they so yeah what I
wanted to ask you it tell us a little
bit more about this that at the end of
your and would you Louise's book the
system's fear of life you have a whole
chapter of sustaining the web of life
and after spending such a long career
really looking into how life works as a
as a process and as a systemic
interconnected process what would you
advise people to pay attention to in
terms of what we need to do as human
beings to redesign as David also nicely
put it that we need to redesign the
human presence and impact on earth
within the lifetime of the generations
in life today and in this process of
redesigning our impact what do we need -
well then you let me say first that this
textbook is half theory and half
applications so there are over 200 pages
of applications to the economy to
politics to environmental activism but
also to you know medicine and health
care management you know various various
other things and the same is true for my
online course the capra course which
begins with the theory with the system's
view of life the nature of systems
thinking and then the systemic
understanding of life and then what does
it mean for a system for your health
what does it mean for the the climate
crisis what does it mean for
economics and so on and so forth so I
think you know from my early years of
writing the turning point in in the
early 1980s I've always had you know
applications in my mind and you know if
you want to put it in extreme way I
could quote Marx who said philosophers
usually interpret the world but the
point is to change it and so in in that
sense I've been a Marxist in in in this
broader sense in in in all my life
because the new understanding the new
paradigm and the change of paradigms has
important social and political
implications and they've always been in
my mind you know since the 1960s so in
answer to your question I think the the
great challenge of our time the central
challenge is to build sustainable
communities to to build communities that
do not interfere with nature's inherent
ability to sustain life
so for billions of years nature has
sustained ecosystems and individual
species and has sustained the processes
of life and human activities especially
since the Industrial Age have interfered
with disability sustained to sustain
life and now we need to very urgently
reconnect with nature cooperate with
nature honor
nature's ability to sustain life and
organize ourselves accordingly and so in
order to do that obviously first we have
to understand how nature sustains life
and that's part of the system's we apply
of the ecological dimension of the
systems we arrive in the
long history of evolution nature's
ecosystems have developed certain basic
principles of sustainability or
principles of ecology to sustain life
you know principles like Network cycles
diversity cooperation partnership and so
on and we need to understand those and
then redesign our physical structures
our business organizations technologies
social institutions accordingly now I
have spent several decades now trying to
explore and understand the basic
principles of ecology and I've come to
the conclusion that you can summarize
all these principles of ecology by
saying nature sustains life by
generating and maintaining communities
community seems to be the key issue here
that we know that no living organism can
exist in isolation and in the long
history of evolution from the very first
bacterial cells which emerged about
three and a half billion years ago from
that point those cells formed
communities known as bacterial colonies
and ever since then Nature has created
and sustained communities at all levels
of life so in the last few years and
this is not in the textbook I didn't
write about this in the textbook which
published in 2014 so in in the last six
years the importance of community has
become ever more important to me and has
come to the foreground of my thinking
ever more and if you want to I can you
know tell you why I think community is
so important reasons so the first one I
mentioned already nature sustains life
by creating and nurturing communities
and if we want to do that then we will
find very soon that one of the greatest
obstacles in the way of creating a
sustainable future is a constant assault
by corporate advertising which tells us
everyday that in order to be happy you
have to consume you have to buy our
products that's what will make you happy
nothing else and some excessive material
consumption which is used by the
corporate world to sustain the illusion
of perpetual growth corporate and
economic growth this excessive
consumption is seen as the way to
happiness now if we can show the true
happiness lies in human relationships
rather than material consumption in
other words in community you know then
this is the biggest and most effective
capitals so so that's the second reason
my community is also also if you which I
know from having lived in an intentional
community if you organize our patterns
of consumption communally you get a
higher standard of life with consumption
yes and that's also about the transition
town movement does the many movements
now who are trying to do that so that's
the second reason the third reason is
that what we need to really live
sustainably and and change the design of
our physical structures and social
institutions we need to learn a lot how
to do that and it's not learning in
terms of just absorbing new information
but it's learning this transformative
transformative learning that really
changes our being our values and in in
my experience community is the most
effective vehicle for transformative
learning learning as a learning
community so those are our three reasons
and there's a fourth one and that is
that something we haven't talked about
yet or implicitly we have but not
explicitly and that is that the change
to a new paradigm is not only a
conceptual problem but it's also a
problem and even more so a problem of
values the problem of ethics and ethics
is usually talked about in relation to
religion or philosophy but there is also
a scientific approach that I have
recently discovered to the question of
ethics and that is that as I said before
nature has sustained life by creating
and nurturing communities and natural
selection has favored those communities
in which the individual members behave
for the benefit of the community as a
whole and in the human realm that's what
we call ethics but it's it's common to
all of life's behavior for the common
good
this is ethical behavior and that means
that ethics is always related to
community so these are several reasons
why communities support Aldo Leopold as
you know in in his wonderful little book
saenko County Almanac from the 1960s and
established as like I'd like hope I
remember the quote correctly a thing is
right if it protects the vitality and
connectivity of the biotic community it
is wrong if it does otherwise right and
so ultimately that's also and even said
it uses the word biotic community you
know basically we need to not just pay
attention in a kind of much more
equitable way a human family but as life
as a community of living beings on this
planet how do we judge our actions based
on that ethic of life or not of course
community is a technical term in the
science of ecology an ecosystem is
defined as a community of multiple
species in interaction with their
nonliving environment what I would add
which I think it's so wonderful because
really it is at the heart from your also
of understanding life as a regenerative
community how do we build regenerative
communities that are sourced from the
uniqueness of place and the uniqueness
of culture in a particular location but
what I personally noticed if I if I look
at what's going on globally in terms of
the the hopeful change movements a lot
of people in have come to a similar
conclusion as I have after spending 15
years working with eco villages and
transition towns and very much focusing
on kind of design for sustainability at
the community scale for many years even
set up the world's first Masters with
heriot-watt University on sustainable
community design and what I began to
realize is that there is as with life
being
nested network of at different scales
and where place is always fractal
meaning what I do locally affects the
region and affects the global then the
one layer that we haven't paid a lot of
attention to because of the mental
colonialism of the nation-state which is
a relatively new invention is the buyer
region the watershed which is where
where most of our species history we've
lived in by original settlement patterns
and in communities at the local level
whether we were nomads or settled and in
when you when you really want to create
the whole systems design that that
creates all the benefits around
renewable energies circular biomaterials
economies and all that to do so at the
scale of a community is difficult also
to do set the scale of the city alone is
difficult but when you put the city or
the community into the context of its
watershed or region it's at that scale
that those communities in that region
collaborate to really creates designs
that are regenerative and actually take
care of the local ecosystem yeah have
you written something about that I I'm
writing more and more about it yes and
and I was just thinking you should also
write about the fact that this in some
way contradicts what many people think
of when they think of community because
they think of global digital communities
and which are important too so how how
to you know interface those to the
global worldwide community you know my
daughter who is 34 as friends all over
the world with whom she's in contact
you know continually and she also has a
large circle of local friends with whom
she goes out so you know trance
to ecosystems we could say that that
developing these economic structures
within a bio region and being inspired
by you know say crystal waters the the
eco village in Australia that was
co-created by my friend Maura gamble
Gamble's the interface between those
levels is something very interesting ya
know what's interesting is that while
you can go back as I don't digressing
here but this isn't have you ever come
across
you know Sir Patrick Geddes you've heard
of him yet
yes yeah and the last book that Geddes
wrote was wither
but another biologist from Aberdeen
University was called and towards a
general biology of life and it it's
published in the 1930s and in it with
the limit of all the science that you
draw upon in the system's view of life
of course wasn't done yet and he
actually was very strongly influenced by
Young Christian Smuts who wrote the book
on holism and he tried something similar
to that grand synthesis but but the
reason why starts talking about get is
is not because of that but but Geddes
was also the first person who as a
biologist like he's known for being one
of the founders of the discipline of
town planning and the scientific study
of sociology and he always said that
cities had to be planned in their region
and in many ways was the first Westerner
to speak about the need for a
bioregional approach and then he
influenced Munford very hard strongly
and one foot in the influenced Ian
McHarg very strongly then they Ian my
heart was kind of a mentor to the early
bio regionalists where you live and
Peter Burke and Raymond Desmond and the
planet run foundation and so in the
1970s there was this first
idea of V inhabitation and Reed
the human presence to the by regional
scale very well yeah it never really
went anywhere for many years
I mean Kirkpatrick's L wrote some
wonderful books about it but in recent
years like if you look the the planetary
health alliance that was funded by the
Rockefeller Foundation as this global
network now they recognized that their
work on planetary health in the link
between human and ecosystems health has
to also happened at the by regional
scale and and then the capital Institute
just launched the regenerative
communities network which is another
network of initiatives around the globe
that want to create bio regional
regenerative economies so today this
there's something really and I think
that's a very fertile ground that needs
to be explored but but to not to digress
any further because we just had the
economy keyword one thing that I would
love for you to just speak a bit about
because for me that was a big insight
and when I first came across this paper
by you and Hazel Henderson from 2009
that you wrote for some I don't know
your body like the British Insurers or
British and but there is this wonderful
paper on the internet if anybody wants
to look at it I'm just saying Fritjof
Capra hazel Henderson qualitative growth
and it pops up as a PDF you can go to my
website freaky of Caprock net and it's
it's in my blog this this notion because
I I feel deeply uncomfortable as a
biologist with the the framing around no
growth D growth anti growth and it's the
type of growth measured with the wrong
type of instruments like GDP and that is
the problem so can you say a little bit
about well you know when I looked at
major problems of the world from a
systemic perspective this was around the
year 2000 when I wrote the book the
hidden
directions and when I realized that they
are all systemically interconnected I
actually drew a conceptual map of all
the interconnections of the problems
which is also reproduced in the textbook
the system's view of life and I realized
that that at the very basis of these
problems is the fundamental dilemma of
the illusion of Perpetual quantitative
growth on a finite planet which is you
know obviously you know an illusion it's
nonsensical to believe the corporations
and economies can can continually grow
and yet you know virtually all our
corporate and academic economists
believe in their politicians of course
so when they look at an economy they say
well two percent growth is OK a 1
percent is bad it's weak you know 3 or 4
percent is a healthy economy and even if
that's 3 or 4 percent of growth is
caused by Wars and catastrophes and
accidents and and means a doubling and
it means a doubling of patterns of
consumption yeah yeah so so this is
obviously an an illusion and so you know
many people have said we have to stop
this we have to build and no growth
economy or D growth in Italy there's a
big movement called decree schita which
is d growth or negative growth and I
agree completely with you from a
biological and ecological standpoint you
can say growth is an essential
characteristic of life all living
organisms grow but not everything grows
at the same time and not everything
grows all the time so in an ecosystem
for instance
while certain things grow others reach
maturity then decline disintegrate and
provide nourishment for new growth in
the next season
like the leaves falling off trees and so
on so what we need is really this kind
of growth and I called it qualitative
growth growth that is multifaceted and
growth that includes inner growth in
terms of an increase of complexity and
maturity and so what we very urgently
need is to qualify growth we need to
distinguish between good growth and bad
growth and then we need to decrease the
bad growth and increase the good growth
and from an ecological point of view
this distinction is very easy and very
simple so bad growth is growth that uses
fossil fuels that includes toxic
substances that consumes excessively
material resources that is destructive
of communities and so on good growth is
the opposite it's the opposite that now
it's growth that nourishes communities
restores ecosystems is based on
renewable resources contains no toxic
chemicals and so on so we need to make
that shift and it's a shift in terms of
tax policies in terms of you know
economic subsidies and and so on you
know that that one thing I can
absolutely can't understand is that
governments today still subsidize fossil
fuels you know to the tune of billions
and billions of dollars this is these
are so-called reverse subsidies and it's
more than 70% still go to fossil and
nuclear and so that's what this mean
meant by qualitative growth no I highly
recommend
to anybody to read the paper of yours
and one other thing that that I would
love to pick up just also to honor a
common friend of ours was sadly died
over ten years ago now and Professor
Brian Goodwin from who I met when he had
started the master's in holistic science
at Omaha college and one of the things
that I learned so much from Brian in in
that time but one of the things that
always struck me was that as one of the
you could say founding fathers of
complexity theory is a mathematical
method medicine and biologist and he
always felt that a central lesson of
complexity was that if you kind of
slightly simplify what a definition of a
complex dynamic system it's any system
that has more than three interacting
variables going back to Ponca lays three
body problem those systems are
fundamentally unpredictable and
uncontrollable beyond certain scales of
space and time and so he said that
they're really an e alluded to it
earlier the the purpose of the
scientific enterprise for so long has
been to predict and control and wrestle
manipulable ax t out of complexity out
of the rest of nature and and Brian made
this point that what we really need is
to know how to participate appropriately
and he said that we this is not
something that we're going to get
through a statistics and quantitative
analysis driven science which is useful
and powerful and and we should continue
to do it but put it in its place and
what we need is a science of quality to
really make this shift and then he drew
on good he drew on complexity and a
number of of lineages from which to
build the signs of qualities
well Brian Goodwin influenced my
thinking enormous ly I met him in the
early 1970s in London and he was a kind
of maverick who had you know outrageous
ideas and in the biological community
people smiled you know and it'll there's
Brian Goodwin you know and and this was
long before complexity theory it was
very unique as you know because he had a
very rich philosophical and artistic
background and he in science was an
evolutionary biologist complexity
theorist and and because he was also a
mathematician he also had a strong
spiritual dimension and that combination
of you know art and literature and
philosophy and spirituality on the one
hand and science and mathematics on the
other is is very unique and so Brian
participated in many of my shoe Maha
courses and we had fabulous discussions
and one statement I remember very well
was that he said complex systems are not
predictable but they are intelligible
and that is just very beautiful
statement that sort of encapsulates the
nature and you know he was completely
right with the science of qualities and
I alluded to that when I talked about
qualitative growth but not only that the
entire systems view of life is is a
science of qualities because it is a
science of patterns a science of
relationships a science of systemic
properties and this is what quality is
quality is a property of the whole which
is not present
in the parts it's a systemic property
for instance my state of health is not
the sum of the health of my heart and
liver and my toes and my teeth
but is a result of the interactions
between those parts and the
relationships between those parts it's
an emergent property a systemic property
this is what qualities are and this is
exactly what the system's we apply this
picking you up on this the health thing
which I think is was one of the big
insights that I also gained through
working with Brian and and it ultimately
led me to when when I wrote my PhD he
also met you know Seton Baxter I met him
at Omaha college and and Seton was the
one who read my slightly oversized
master's thesis which was 300 pages long
that's effing didn't even want to read
the whole thing and said cut it down
that's that's a PhD and and Seton came
back and said look I I'll find a
scholarship for you if he ever wanted to
do a PhD and so I a couple of years
later ended up doing my PhD with Seton
in a design school and I thought that it
was going to be on design for
sustainability and then being influenced
by your work being influenced by Brian's
work by Stephan Harding and all the
wonderful people that I'd met at Omaha
college um I actually realized that when
we talk about sustainability we talk
about the pattern that connects as
Bateson would have called it and when we
ask what is it that we're trying to
sustain we're trying to sustain the web
of life the regenerative community and
so another word of saying that is health
systemic health exactly as you just
described it and I used this this notion
of health being an emergent property at
different scales across the complex
dynamic system is a systemic property
that that has fractal-like its cellular
health organelle body health family
health community health ecosystems
health planet and I used this too
to work with what what I called the
scales of design Minh I don't know I
wanted to ask you are you familiar with
the work of a guy called Aaron Antonov
ski an Israeli health scientist no he he
did a lot of research on Holocaust
survivors and looked at what was the the
uniqueness that enable people to go
through enormous trauma and still be
able to go on and and also how people
different people responded to stresses
that would make some people ill and died
and other people would survive and he
developed in a book called health stress
and coping in the 1960s in new approach
to health rather than a pathogenic
approach to health which is looking at
what drives the disease and and dealing
with symptoms so that the Roman law no
allopathic approach he said we need a
solute or genic approach to health we
need to look at and what are the
conditions because health is this
dynamic balance you constantly get viral
vectors and bacterial vectors trying to
distract and that that is my definition
of the systems you of health health is a
state of dynamic balance which involves
biological dimensions social dimensions
and ecological dimensions if you send
you some links or snd actually a
Symington whole book on saluted Genesis
that's basically what the jello to
generate approach is about okay there's
one last question thank you so much
there's marathon conversation and I just
really wanted to name one more person in
this context of our conversation who has
been another elder of mine like you and
Brian in in putting me on my path and
and that's David or who I first met at
Juma hawala was on the Masters course
and he and John Todd and Nancy ejected
and offered a short course on ecological
design and that's when I first
understood the power of design in
bringing it like human intention
expressed through interactions
and relationships bringing this new
holistic worldview and systems view of
life into action is through design and
let me just David over here that this is
what I use in in all my work he defines
design as the shaping of flows of energy
and matter for human purposes that's an
ecological definition of design and then
he defined defines ecological design or
eco design as meshing those human
purposes with the natural flows and
patterns in nature so that has been very
inspired that yeah basically that put me
on my path like I was somewhat impatient
and frustrated having learned the
wonderful theory of holistic science and
I wanted to say but the world's burning
how do we put this interaction and
that's when I realized meeting John Todd
and and also Nancy Todd and David and
that ecological design was what I wanted
to dedicate my future to him
and so I wrote this PhD and at the end
of it David actually ended up being my
external exam examiner and and it was
all over and done I went to see him at
Oberlin College in in Ohio and I did an
interview which would still floats about
on YouTube somewhere in 2006 with him
where I asked him about the original
question was actually about the
dimension of spirituality and the sacred
in the transition that we now had to do
to redesign the human impact on earth
before our very young species would die
an early death and um in his answer he
said something that was just basically
the seed for designing regenerative
culture ten years before I wrote the
book he gave me the seed for that he
said before we can ask or answer
appropriately the
the what we need to do to create a
sustainable human presence or how we
might go about doing it we need to ask
ourselves a more complicated question a
much more difficult question which is
what is it about human beings that makes
us worth sustaining and that just for me
was a like a big question to mull on for
a long time and I would love for you to
to give us your take from your long life
and having met some of the most
inspiring human beings in my perspective
on the planet in the last 50 years and
what what is it that you think is our
unique contribution as human beings and
why is it would it be a shame if we died
early as a species well I think I would
give you an an answer from the
perspective of evolution what the
life-forms that are worth sustaining are
actually the ones that are sustained in
evolution and they are the ones that
best contribute to the continual
regeneration and unfolding of life so to
the extent that we contribute to that we
are birth sustaining and we will be
sustained by nature if we do that to the
extent that we are not contributing
which is you know much more at present
and in our contributions we will not be
sustained now if you look at the history
of evolution you can see that the
average life span of a species from its
emergence to its extinction is about
five million years so on the average the
species that have lived much longer and
others much shorter but the average is
about 5 million years now Homo sapiens
has lived for about thirty thousand
years so we are new comers still on the
planet
we have lived less than 1% of the
average lifespan of his species so it is
much too early to tell whether we are
worth sustaining or not but you know at
present it doesn't look very good you
know we can definitely say that so I
mean this this this is a dire question
and I would say that my sense of hope
for sustainability and the continuation
of humanity on the planet has been
inspired very much by Watts love hobble
the great Czech playwright and former
president of the Czech Republic and
hobble wrote something where he turns
the assessment or they the the
exploration of hope into a sort of
meditation on the nature of hope and he
says that hope is a dimension of the
soul not the result of a certain
assessment of the state of the world and
he writes and he wrote this while he was
imprisoned as a dissident by the Soviet
regime and let me read to you what what
he writes about hope he writes hope is
not the conviction that something will
turn out well but the certainty that
something makes sense regardless of how
it turns out so this has inspired me
tremendously for the last years many
years and it's hard trying to live my
life yeah I would second that and they
also like days something about
in I you know get people finally going
into the street and raising an alarm
about the imminence of not just we're
already in the middle middle of
catastrophic climate change but we have
a opportunity and the window of
opportunity is closing to avoid
cataclysmic climate change where we get
to a point where basically higher life
forms such as ours will not be on this
planet for a while and I'm facing almost
like a species level rite of passage
facing the real possibility of death at
this early point in this jump to the
next stage of them being a more mature
species a more mature member in the
community of life I often find that what
we actually asked also came back to is
where you also started we're talking
about the cup of course earlier the bed
today there is some kind of spiritual
subtext to all of this that that brings
us back into not just what we do but how
we are into our being and our connection
like this wonderful conversation we just
had and to celebrate this they say like
for me it's that level of connection
that is why we're worth sustaining as a
species that we that we can write poems
about love like me rooted it and that we
can write symphonies or songs like the
ode to joy' that was written by Sheila
and then put to music by Beethoven there
is some grandeur there is some beauty in
us and we have proven particularly our
indigenous brothers and sisters have
proven in many places around the world
that we can also be gardeners that we
can have a healing influence on
ecosystems like for example the Amazon
rainforest being partially human made by
by its only inhabitants so yeah from for
me it's it's it's it's a coming back to
the moment and an appreciation and and
so deep appreciation also to it or yeah
yeah we should we should continue having
these conversations and
and you know continue to build these
communities of systemic thinkers and
activists as I do in my capra course and
you do in your networks and you work so
let's continue
we were regeneration rising trim tabs
United it's what I sign my unions with
these so thank you so much this was
already rich wonderful I'm just going to
stop the recording and then we say